<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meroveus a Prince of the blood-royal of France A novel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1834</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217812</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829455</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829455</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33895</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33895)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1919:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meroveus a Prince of the blood-royal of France A novel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 115, [5] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for R. Bentley and M. Magnes, in Russel-street in Covent-Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With [5] p. of advertisements bound at end.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; tightly bound, pages stained slightly affecting text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MEROVEUS A PRINCE OF THE Blood-Royal of <hi>FRANCE.</hi> A NOVEL.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of a globe</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Bentley,</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:3"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable THE COUNTESSE OF <hi>OXFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Univerſal Admiration Your Ladyſhip has ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the World, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:33895:4"/>inſpired a young Prince with a Curioſity to ſee ſo many Wonders as Fame does Your Ladyſhip the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to relate, He is come from beyond Sea with hopes not only of having leave to ſatisfie the Ambition He has of paying Homage to ſo many Excellencies, but
<pb facs="tcp:33895:4"/>likewiſe, if you can think fit, Madam, to allow Him a favourable Audience, He does not queſtion but to make appear, that his Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes are of ſuch a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as both to merit and engage Your Ladyſhips Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Protection. Both His Commiſſion and Paſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port
<pb facs="tcp:33895:5"/>to Your Ladyſhip have ſomething in them ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, that as One has wherewith to raiſe Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo the Other has to create Veneration in all People. For He is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſed, Madam, to a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy whoſe Family has ever, and is ſtill at this day
<pb facs="tcp:33895:5"/>fruitful in <hi>Hero's,</hi> and who has likewiſe the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of being united to One that has filled the Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of all Ages with its Extraordinary Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and miraculous Inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Conſtant Loyalty, wherein they have been ſo zealouſly followed by the
<pb facs="tcp:33895:6"/>preſent Earl, that the Beſt of Subjects and Greateſt of Men may be proud of imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating his Conduct and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: Yet, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all theſe Invitations, this Prince does acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that he was incited to this Addreſs more by Your Ladyſhips own Merit
<pb facs="tcp:33895:6"/>and Luſtre, than all theſe Advantages of Extraction and Alliance: It was a Beauty, Madam, above de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, a Wit beyond all imagination, and theſe at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by a benign Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, an Affability, a Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and all and none but thoſe Qualities which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure
<pb facs="tcp:33895:7"/>Reſpect and Acclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that made him ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious of laying himſelf at Your Ladyſhips Feet, and to beg leave to declare the Devotion with which I am, Madam,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Ladyſhips Moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, <hi>F. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:33895:7"/>
            <head>MEROVEUS A PRINCE OF THE <hi>Blood-Royal</hi> OF FRANCE.</head>
            <div n="1-57" type="pages">
               <p>THE Poſterity of <hi>Clovis</hi> the Great begun to poſſeſs the Throne; <hi>Clotarius</hi> the youngeſt of his Children, remaining alone of all his Brothers to ſettle the riſing Monarchy of the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:33895:8"/>
                  <hi>French,</hi> left for his Succeſſours four Sons, who ſhared the Crown between them. <hi>Cherebert,</hi> being the eldeſt, had for his part the Kingdom of <hi>Paris,</hi> and its depencies. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tran,</hi> that of <hi>Orleans: Chilperic,</hi> that of <hi>Soiſſons;</hi> and <hi>Sigebert</hi> that of <hi>Metz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though that Union is ſomething rare between perſons of their Rank, thoſe four Princes lived a long time in a perfect intelligence in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of their States, and the tenderneſſes of Blood were ever more powerful in their hearts, than any ſentiment of ambition and jealouſie. They did not think the alliance of any neighbouring Prince, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to them for the ſupport of their Thrones; wherefore when they reſolved to leave Heirs, they ſought not for Women elſewhere than amongſt their Subjects, and as merit was the only thing that they conſidered, they applyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves indifferently to Perſons in
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:33895:8"/>whom they found moſt Charms, Beauty and Wit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cherebert,</hi> whom <hi>Clotarius</hi> his Father had cauſed to marry <hi>Ingo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berga</hi> againſt his will, divorced him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from her to take in her place <hi>Merofleda,</hi> a Merchants Daughter: <hi>Gontrand</hi> made the like choice in his States: <hi>Sigebert</hi> lived a long time without any engagement; and as for <hi>Chilperick,</hi> he marryed <hi>Andeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>era,</hi> the truth is a Maid of mean Birth, but whom Heaven had only deprived of the advantages of Blood, that the quickneſs of her Wit, the greatneſs of her Soul, and the Charms of her Beauty might be the more admired: <hi>Chilperick</hi> had by her ſeveral Children and amongſt others a Prince called <hi>Meroveus. Cherebert</hi> after having reigned ſix years, dyed in the Caſtle of <hi>Blaye</hi> in <hi>Xaintonge:</hi> he left no male Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: Inſomuch that the three Princes his Brothers ſhared his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom between them: but as not one
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:33895:9"/>of them would conſent to yield <hi>Paris</hi> to an other, it was reſolved that City ſhould remain neutral, that it ſhould be equally to all three, and that not one might enter it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the conſent of the others, upon pain of loſing the part he had in the ſucceſſion of <hi>Cherebert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Affair thus regulated, thoſe Princes paſſed ſtill ſeveral years in an agreeable Society, and only made uſe of their Arms to repulſe the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of Strangers their common Enemies. But Fortune that uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly takes delight in deſtroying all that is not its Work, let them only ſo long injoy this ſweet tranquility that their Diviſion might be the more ſenſible to them.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Meroveus</hi> was ſeventeen years old, when one <hi>Fredegonda</hi> came into the ſervice of Queen <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douera. Meroveus</hi> and <hi>Fredegonda</hi> having the greateſt part in this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, it will not be out of the way to give a light Idea of them, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:33895:9"/>they may be the better known.</p>
               <p>It may be ſaid that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> was one of the moſt capricious Works that Nature was capable of produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing: there was in her a confuſed heap of good and ill Qualities, all of them extraordinary: but as her Virtues poſſeſſed but the leaſt part in her Soul, they ever ſerved only to ſet off her Vices. That which rendered the world ſometimes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſed in her favour, was that what ſhe had beſt, diſcovered it ſelf at firſt. Thoſe who had once ſeen her and heard her diſcourſe, could hardly perſuade themſelves afterwards that Heaven would mingle ſo rare Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections amongſt ſo great Defects. And it muſt be avowed that ſhe knew admirable well how to ſet off the Talents ſhe was Miſtreſs of. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was Beauty in all its luſtre better managed and more ingeniouſly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed to its Deſigns. Never did Wit with more artifice uſe all the graces of eloquence to perſuade; and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:33895:10"/>never any heart ſo cunningly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the language of its ſighs, for the gaining the tenderneſs of a Prince. She thought it indifferent to follow the courſe of Virtue or to ſtray from it, and ſhe only ſought it when ſhe judged it might favour her enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizes. Ambition, Revenge, and Jealouſie diſpoſed by turns of her Soul. Love was not unknown to her, but he had never ſo great an Empire over her as to betray any of theſe paſſions. The greateſt crimes raiſed no horrour in her, ſhe reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of them without pain for the ſatisfying her deſires. Fear had lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle place in her heart, becauſe that her Policy was to prevent all thoſe whom ſhe believed might do her hurt, and a light ſuſpition was ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the ſacrificing them to her ſafety. Her reſentments could not be ſoftned by time. Her hatred was only extinguiſhed in the blood of the perſon from whom ſhe ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to have received any outrage.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:33895:10"/>Deceit, diſſimulation, perfidiouſneſs and lying, were alſo many Veils which concealed from the moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrating Eyes, all the foldings of her heart. In fine to give her Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture with one ſtroke, it is ſufficient to ſay that ſelf-love was the only rule ſhe thought worthy of being imbraced in the world.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> on the contrary, was one of the moſt accompliſhed Princes that <hi>France</hi> had yet ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. It was to have been wiſhed that Heaven had brought him into the world in a leſs elevated degree; that not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing invironed with that dazling pomp, all his perfections might have been more nearly contemplated, and his merit judged of by it ſelf. It was not neceſſary to proceed to his Soul to find ſomething in him worthy of admiration. From all the Features that Nature had printed in his Face, there reſulted I know not what kind of Air which inſpired love and reſpect in all thoſe who
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:33895:11"/>approached him. Never any Prince gave ſo fair hopes, and in whoſe Eyes were read greater things. At ſo tender an age he had already ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalized himſelf in Arms, and the Lawrels he had gathered in ſeveral, &amp; important, occaſions, made all the world doubt if the eaſineſs of fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was not rather born with him, than formed by a long habit.</p>
               <p>It ſeemed that ſo many fair quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ought to have ſubdued Fortune to the happineſs of this Prince: Yet that cruel Enemy of Virtue made it on the contrary appear that it is in vain that Nature ſtrives to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain its Works, when Fortune un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakes to attack them: It was its will that the unfortunate <hi>Meroveus</hi> ſhould ſearch Poſterity for a famous example of its power, as well as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had not ſeen him twice when ſhe became infinitely in love with him; and as ſhe ſaw that this paſſion was but too conformable
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:33895:11"/>to her ambition, ſhe wholly aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned her ſelf to it with all manner of joy. She fancied that he being of an age that has little force to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt paſſions, and wherein a heart is eaſily ſurprized by Love when it meets with a proper object, he would hardly eſcape her artifices: but all her cunning and all her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs was in vain: <hi>Meroveus,</hi> after having a long time avoided her ſnares, at length ſeeing that ſhe one day ſpake to him openly of her love, rallied her publickly for it, and told her that to acknowledge the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhe had for him, he would marry her to one of his Officers.</p>
               <p>Theſe words produced in <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda</hi>'s Soul a furious vexation and an immortal hatred, which was the ſource of all the diſgraces of <hi>Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veus,</hi> and which led him to his Grave. But as the force of this wicked Woman lay in artifices, ſhe knew ſo well how to diſſemble in that occaſion, that ſhe ſmiled at the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:33895:12"/>Princes anſwer, and even thanked him very civily. As ſhe knew that on the firſt impreſſions, good or bad, that others have received from us, depend oftentimes all the judgments that are made in the ſequel; ſhe at firſt affected a conduct with <hi>Andou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>era,</hi> which procured her the eſteem and confidence of her Miſtreſs, and the jealouſie of her Companions. All her actions were governed by a complaiſance full of ſweetneſs, a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful ſubmiſſion to all that was exacted from her, and an earneſtneſs ever new to acquit her ſelf of the leaſt things her devoir engaged her to.</p>
               <p>It is an uſual defect in all good Souls to judg of others by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: as they are incapable of any diſguiſe, they fancy they ſee in the actions of others as much fincerity as in their own, and this imprudent goodneſs makes them oftentimes take for an effuſion of heart, what proceeds only from an addreſs of Wit.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:33895:12"/>
               <p>The falſe and deceitful appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> ſo ſurprized all the affections of <hi>Andouera,</hi> that this good Princeſs fancyed that ſhe could not do enough to make known to her the ſenſe ſhe had of her ſervices. She propoſed her for a model to all her other Maids of Honour, ſhe filled the Court with her praiſes, and the King was eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally dayly importuned with them; ſo true it is that we often run pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitately to our own ruine, and we become our ſelves the contrivers of our own unhappineſs.</p>
               <p>Though the Princeſs <hi>Andouera</hi> had already ſpent more than eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years in marriage, ſhe was ſtill capable of charming, and neither that long ſpace of time, nor her Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings In, which are uſually the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers of Beauty, had worn out any thing of that ſurprizing luſtre which conquers hearts. But as deſires and hopes are the only things which maintain Love, and that nothing is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:33895:13"/>more capable of making us diſreliſh an object than a long and peaceable poſſeſſion. <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s paſſion for the Queen did nothing now but lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh, and thoſe devouring flames which the firſt fight of that Princeſs had kindled in his Heart, were as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed in the injoyment of her pleaſures.</p>
               <p>The reputation of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Wit and Beauty gave him one day the curioſity of conſidering and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing her attentively. It was in that occaſion that this cunning Maid neglected nothing of all ſhe judged proper for engaging the King. She fought for Darts in her Eyes fit to diſcover the way to his Heart, and drain'd all the lights of her Wit to charm the Princes.</p>
               <p>It was not neceſſary to imploy ſo much addreſs upon a man who ran to meet his Chains, and who longed that a new paſſion might renew his deſires. <hi>Chilperick</hi> told <hi>Fredegonda</hi> upon his leaving her, that he was
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:33895:13"/>very much ſatisfied with her diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and that he would do her ſome kindneſs in a very ſhort time. In effect, he ſent for her ſome days after by his truſtieſt Officer, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having repeated to her the ſame thing, he added for the declaring to her his paſſion, that he had found in her more Beauty and Wit than he ought to have. deſired for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; that it was to Love ſhe was going to owe all the favours he ſhould heap upon her; but as his happineſs depended on her, ſhe ought to contribute to it in giving him ſenſible and convincing marks of a mutual tenderneſs; and above all, that ſhe ſhould carefully conceal this Gallantry from the Queen, who would not fail to be enraged at it.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Fredegonda</hi> changed, as ſhe pleaſed, the motions of her Face, ſhe ſeemed at that moment ſo modeſt, that it helped to inflame the Kings deſires. She made him know that ſhe deſired nothing ſo ardently as to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:33895:14"/>make appear to him the joy ſhe felt to ſee her ſelf beloved by ſo great a Prince; but that he was not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act any thing from her that her vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue might diſallow.</p>
               <p>The King was not yet ſo blinded with his paſſion, but that he conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that it ever becomes a Woman to make ſome reſiſtance, and not to yield ſo ſoon. He was not willing to preſs her more that day: he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented himſelf with telling her that they would talk of it more than once, and that he would give her time to think of it. Having ſpoken theſe words, he took out a Table-Book with Gold-Covers ſet with Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amonds, which he made her a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of.</p>
               <p>He had hardly left her, than that his imagination repreſenting her to him yet more fair than ſhe was, made him ſenſible of new returns of Love, and was extream impatient to ſee her again; ſo that the next morning, while the Queen reſted,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:33895:14"/>he ſent his Confident to tell her he deſired to ſpeak with her, and ſhe immediately went to the Cabinet where he waited for her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> knowing better how to dive into the hearts of others than they into hers, eaſily perceived that <hi>Chilperick</hi> was too much a ſlave to his Love, to be able ever to maſter it. Wherefore, as it was Ambition that made her act, ſhe did not amuſe her ſelf to flatter his paſſion with frivoulous hopes, but had the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to tell him, that if he deſired ſhe ſhould anſwer it, he muſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry her; that her birth was not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to <hi>Andouera</hi>'s; that nothing was ſo common with all Princes, as divorce, that neither reaſons nor pretext would be wanting for the furthering the deſign; that this procedure towards <hi>Andouera,</hi> was not unjuſt, that it was enough for her to have held ſo glorious a rank near twenty years; that for her part when ſhe ſhould as long have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:33895:15"/>ſhared his Crown, with him, ſhe would endeavour to comfort her ſelf if an other took her place; that in fine, he might aſſure himſelf, that nothing but his Faith could obtain from her what he pretended. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe words ſhe went out of the Cabinet, and left the Prince in a mortal trouble.</p>
               <p>Though it be eaſie for Love to become all on a ſudden Maſter of a Heart, and that one moment alone is ſufficient for it to chaſe away all that oppoſes its deſigns, yet it does not reign there ſoveraignly, until af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſeveral ſtrifes, for the rendring its Victory the more illuſtrious, and the more powerfully engage reaſon to ſupport its intereſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick</hi> found his mind a long time wavering between his Devoir and his new paſſion: if the pleaſures he hoped to injoy in the poſſeſſion of <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> inclined him towards her; on the other ſide the Image of his Glory ſtained by ſo ſhameful
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:33895:15"/>a Divorce, and the innocence of <hi>Andouera</hi> were powerful curbs to ſtop the rapidity of his Vows. The great marks of Love that he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from that good Princeſs, her paſſionate tenderneſs, her ardent ſighs, her tranſports ever new, her application; cares and complaiſance, knocked every Moment at the Door of his Heart, to put him in mind of recovering a lawful Empire.</p>
               <p>But as it is much more eaſie to ſtray from our Devoir, than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to it when we have been once out of the way, all theſe objects, after having for ſome time ſhaked <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s mind, diſappeared at length to let Love triumph. All that virtue could obtain from him, was that he ſhould do what he could to perſuade <hi>Fredogonda,</hi> before that he reſolved to be divorced from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douera.</hi> Whereupon he beſieged that imperious Miſtreſs with all manner of Arms. He joyned to the luſtre of his perſon all the diſcourſes
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:33895:16"/>of the moſt ſubmiſſive Lovers; and without doubt, a woman leſs ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious than <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> would not have been able to have held out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſo many importunities; but that haughty paſſion had too deep roots in her heart, to ſuffer her to be ſeduced by other impreſſions. She was ever deaf to the Prayers of <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick,</hi> and after having a long time denyed him, and even refuſed the Preſents he would have made her; She once told him very ſharply that he was very ſcrupulous, and very fearful, not to dare to take that liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to become happy, which the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of ſo many Princes authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and which <hi>Cherebert</hi> his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had himſelf practiſed.</p>
               <p>There is no injury which ſo ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly touches Kings, as the reproach of fear: as boldneſs is the firſt mark of courage, they imagine for the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, making appear the greatneſs of their Souls, they ought to give their power its full ſcope, inſomuch that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:33895:16"/>what moves them to unlawful acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, is oftentimes only a vain glory of making known that they are capable of undertaking all things. <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda</hi>'s words had ſo much force up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s heart, that they part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined him intirely to marry her. His pride repreſented to him, that to make the impreſſion in the mind of that Maid, and of all his People, of a ſtrong Idea of his inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence, he ought not to defer his Divorce from <hi>Andouera;</hi> and Love applauding the ſentiments of his pride, perſuaded him that he ought no longer to ballance the eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his happineſs, ſince it would on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly coſt him one crime, which the moſt natural of all paſſions had ever rendered excuſable. He told his Miſtreſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that he very well foreſaw, that he muſt conſent to what ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and that he would quickly make her ſee, that it was not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fear that had made him re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt ſo long.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:33895:17"/>
               <p>This diſcourſe ſo puft up <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda</hi>'s vanity, that ſhe began from that moment to fancy her ſelf Crowned, and to act like a Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign with all people. The Queen who was not long without percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it, was the moſt of all concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at this Change. As ſhe had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver found any thing but ſubmiſſion, and reſpect in <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perious Air with which ſhe ſpake to her, could not enough ſurprize her. She ſeveral times made her gentle remonſtrances, and ſeeing it was to no purpoſe, ſhe one day pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to threatnings.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> being no longer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any confideration, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſharply, and left the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, telling her, that ſhe had no longer right to uſe thoſe terms, that her time was paſſed, and that others was going to begin. Theſe words were clear enough to explain to the Queen, <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s new engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but being ſtill blinded by her
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:33895:17"/>eaſineſs, they only plunged her into a great diſquiet.</p>
               <p>As ſhe was in theſe agitations, <hi>Meroveus,</hi> her Son, came to her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment, to make known to her the firſt news of her Diſgrace. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus</hi> having a penetrating Wit had a long time perceived <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Deſigns; but being he had ever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved, that the King would have no leſs power than he, to reſiſt her ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices, he had not thought fit to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm the Queen with the recital of a thing of little conſequence, and wherein he did not foreſee, that the Glory and Love of that Princeſs were to be one day equally interreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>An Officer of the Kings Bed-Chamber, deploring the approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing misfortune of <hi>Andouera,</hi> having given notice to the Prince of what paſſed, <hi>Meroveus</hi> believed it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to acquaint the Queen ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with it, that ſhe might joyn with him to avoid the ſtorm that was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:33895:18"/>to powder upon her. The poor Princeſs having learn'd <hi>Meroveus</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal diſcourſe, fell into a ſwoon in his arms, and it was to little purpoſe, that the Prince remained pious in this Rencounter, and that he left her not in that oppreſſion, being, when ſhe came to her ſelf, ſhe was the more ſenſible of her misfortune, and delivered her mind up to the moſt cruel attacks of Grief.</p>
               <p>They reſolved to go find the King out immediately, and to remonſtrate to him the diſorders this unhappy paſſion would produce, if he reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſatisfie it at the expence of his Glory. Approaching the Kings A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment they perceived at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance through the Glaſs Windows <hi>Fredegonda</hi> holding a Table-Book in her hands.</p>
               <p>After having ſtole ſoftly to the Window, <hi>Andouera</hi> perceived it was the Kings Table-Book, in which he ever ſet down his moſt ſecret De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:33895:18"/>
               <p>At this ſight the Queen was ſeiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a lively reſentment; ſhe commanded <hi>Fredegonda</hi> to open to her the Door, which ſhe refuſed to do, threatning ſhe would complain to the King if any violence was done her.</p>
               <p>Theſe inſolent words increaſed the Queens vexation; and <hi>Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veus</hi> being tranſported with anger, having broken the Windows, leap'd furiouſlly into the Cabinet, ſnatch'd the Table-Book out of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s hands, and went to the Queen, who returned with him, to her Chamber to examine it. After having turned over ſeveral Leaves without finding any thing, ſhe read in one place theſe Verſes written by <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s one hand, and which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in the beginning of his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for <hi>Fredegonda:</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:33895:19"/>
                  <q>
                     <l>Love only pleaſes for a time,</l>
                     <l>At length we're weary of its Chain.</l>
                     <l>Virtue the moſt ſevere, ſublime,</l>
                     <l>From a new choice can't oft reſtrain.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>And below theſe Verſes, <hi>Andou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>era</hi> found theſe of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s hand writing.
<q>
                     <l>When we have charm'd a great and mighty King,</l>
                     <l>Muſt we have nothing but his pant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Heart?</l>
                     <l>His Empire ought to be our Offering,</l>
                     <l>E're we do eaſe his fiery raging ſmart;</l>
                     <l>Yes, yes, ambition is the brighteſt Flame,</l>
                     <l>What Woman wants it, is I'me ſure to blame.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>What became of her after having read theſe ſtabbing words? It was then that this deplorable Princeſs took a full view of her misfortunes,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:33895:19"/>and that ſhe no longer doubted that <hi>Chilperick</hi> was charmed with <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda,</hi> but even that this wicked Maid had already much ſhaken his Virtue, to engage him to marry her. She run as diſtracted, accompanied by <hi>Meroveus,</hi> to the Kings Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. When they came to his Chamber Door, the Guards refuſed to let them in, and told them they had Orders not to let any one ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever enter without acquainting the King.</p>
               <p>After having learn'd that they were there, he came to them contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to his cuſtom. <hi>Andouera,</hi> at the ſight of <hi>Chilperick,</hi> let fall a torrent of Tears; all the Graces painted at that time, in her Face, an eloquent Grief, capable of moving the moſt barbarous heart; and without doubt <hi>Chilperick's</hi> would not have been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible, if he had not been full of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Charms, whom he had newly quitted.</p>
               <p>The Queen with a languiſhing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:33895:20"/>Voice, and which was every moment interrupted by her ſighs, told the King, that the love ſhe bore him, rather than her own intereſts, engaged her to make known to him how ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully he was going to ſtain his Glory by the irregularity of his Paſſion. She pray'd him to conſider what could be the nature of the affection that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had for his Perſon, and to judg of it by the Verſes ſhe had made upon that ſubject. Having ſpoken theſe words, ſhe preſented the Table-Book to the King.</p>
               <p>That Object filled his Soul with ſpite and confuſion, and made him fall into furious motions of choler againſt the Queen. He did not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit her to ſpeak any more; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupting her, he told her angrily, that he could never have believed, ſhe would have been ſo bold as to have done violence to perſons whom he honoured with his affection, even to force from them, the Teſtimonies he had been willing to give them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:33895:20"/>thereof; that ſhe as well as <hi>Mero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veus</hi> ſhould pay dear for this affront. That as for his paſſion for <hi>Fredegon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> if ſhe found it was ſo great a crime, it was for her herſelf to expiate it, ſince ſhe had been the principal cauſe; that he ſhould never have conceived the leaſt deſire of ſpeaking to that Maid, if ſhe had not dayly ſtun'd him with her praiſes; that it was her great importunity alone that had ſtirred up her curioſity; that her dayly diſcourſes repeated in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of her Rival, had made him inſenſibly love her before he had conſidered her; in fine, that ſhe had no body to blame but her ſelf for her misfortune, ſince ſhe had woven with her own hands the Bonds which were going to break theirs.</p>
               <p>This outraging reproach pierced the very Soul of poor <hi>Andouera:</hi> all the words it contained were ſo much the more ſenſible to her, for that they were true, and that ſhe acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged ſhe had been the fatal inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:33895:21"/>of her own ruine. The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of grief did not leave her force enough to ſpeak: but her eyes and ſighs declared all the juſt indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with which ſhe was ſeized. <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus</hi> was not ſo moderate as ſhe, or rather his reſentment was not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to deprive him of the uſe of his voice; he told the King that ſince he was reſolved to puſh things to that extremity, he ſaw himſelf conſtrained to be once wanting in the reſpect that he owed him as his Son and his Subject, for the prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a diſorder that was going to fall upon all the Royal Family.</p>
               <p>This menace inflamed <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s anger; he cauſed the Queen and <hi>Meroveus</hi> to be ſeized, commanded they ſhould be ſhut up apart, and cauſed Guards to be ſet at their Chamber doors, with expreſs order to let no body enter. After which he returned to the Cabinet where <hi>Fredegonda</hi> expected him. She at firſt affected a falſe pity for <hi>Andouera,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:33895:21"/>and told <hi>Chilperick</hi> that it was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will that ſhe cauſed ſo much diſorder in the Court; but ſince it was for the better ſetling the happineſs of her King, ſhe did not repent it: but that it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and even neceſſary, ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make an end of the Work, and to remove the Queen while that people's minds were already prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for that rupture.</p>
               <p>The too eaſie <hi>Chilperick,</hi> beſotted with his paſſion, conſented to all <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s propoſitions, and would not follow any other rule than her will. He agreed with her to ſend the Queen to the City of <hi>Mans.</hi> After having haſtily made her a ſmall Equipage, he cauſed her to depart at two days end, without ſuffering her to bid him farewel, nor even to ſpeak with <hi>Meroveus.</hi> That innocent and deplorable Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs went thus from <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared as a wretched Victim, that her love for an unfaithful Man was
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:33895:22"/>going to conſume by little and little. So long as ſhe could perceive the Walls of that City, ſhe eyed it, &amp; ſent it continually her ſighs. But as ſoon as ſhe was out of ſight, ſhe paſſed over in her thoughts all that had paſſed at Court: ſhe re-called into her memory, all the Graces and Favours ſhe had ſo often ſo prodigally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon her Rival, and for which ſhe had not expected ſo fatal a recompence: but that which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed her pain was, that ſhe was not allowed at her departure to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Prince her Son, whom ſhe cheriſhed with a tenderneſs worthy of her.</p>
               <p>When ſhe arrived at <hi>Mans,</hi> though that Fame had already car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed thither the news of her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, all the City was in Arms to receive her, and did her all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours that they owed, not only to their true Queen, but as to a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who had ever reigned more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignly over all their minds by
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:33895:22"/>her Virtues, than by the Title ſhe had born.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> having learn'd his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers removal, conceived a mortal hatred againſt <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to be revenged on her, let what would come on it: but his impriſonment not permitting him to attempt the execution of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, he was conſtrained to ſtifle them. The King not being willing to keep always from the Eyes of the Court, a Prince upon whom all the people founded their greateſt hopes, bethought himſelf of an artifice to ſet him at liberty: but he put him in ſuch a poſture, as not to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend any thing he could do againſt <hi>Fredegonda:</hi> He made known to <hi>Meroveus,</hi> that if he made any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt upon her, he would immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately revenge himſelf on the Princeſs his Mother, and that the leaſt Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace that ſhould eſcape from him, ſhould be the ſentence of <hi>Andouera's</hi>'s Death. It was upon theſe harſh
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:33895:23"/>Conditions that the Prince was let out of Priſon. The ſight of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy did every moment increaſe his hatred, and he would not have been able to have forborn the abandoning himſelf to ſome violence, if the Queens intereſt had not ever retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the pomp of the Kings Marriage with <hi>Fredegonda</hi> was preparing. This ambitious Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man triumphing in her ſelf, floated then in joy, and imagined her ſelf already at the point of Soveraignty. But fortune which delights in ſelling her Favours dear, ſtill exacted from her great Crimes, before it mounted her upon the Throne.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Huns,</hi> who placed all their glory in making Courſes and Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions upon their Neighbours, took a reſolution of ſeizing <hi>Auſtraſia.</hi> To that end they marched out of <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonia,</hi> and came with powerful Troops to attack King <hi>Sigebert,</hi> who prepared to repulſe them courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:33895:23"/>But at the ſame time there happened to him other Affairs which conſtrained him to treat of Peace with the <hi>Huns,</hi> not very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to him, and ſuch as his great courage would not have ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in another conjuncture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> whoſe ambition in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and ſeeing no more obſtacles to hinder her from reigning with <hi>Chilperick,</hi> carryed her deſires much farther, and believed ſhe ought not to let ſo fair an occaſion ſlip, of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging the bounds of an Empire ſhe fancied already belonged to her. She remonſtrated to <hi>Chilperick,</hi> that while the King of <hi>Auſtraſia</hi> was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied in defending himſelf againſt the <hi>Huns,</hi> it would be eaſie for him to invade his Territories, that he ought not to be retained by any vain ſcruple, and to ſtop at weak conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of Friendſhip and tenderneſs; that nothing was ſo glorious as the Title of Conquerour; In fine, that it was great to be in a poſture of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:33895:24"/>Law to others, and of making Subjects, even upon the Throne.</p>
               <p>It was Ambition that dictated this diſcourſe to <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> but ſhe had likewiſe other very powerful conſiderations to move her to it. As Policy was the principal reſort that ſet her mind agoing, her paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for a Scepter, did not hinder her from fore-ſeeing that her Marriage would not fail to diſpleaſe the Princes her Brothers, and upon their perſuaſion he would ſooner or later be obliged to be divorced from her; Inſomuch that ſhe had already for ſome time ſought means fit for the breaking the Union that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them when this was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. She did not at all doubt but that <hi>Gontran</hi> King of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who loved Peace and Juſtice, would ardently imbrace <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s Party, when be came to know the equity of his Cauſe; and thus ſhe judged that the ſucceſs of this War, let it be what it would, muſt needs be advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to her.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:33895:24"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick,</hi> who did nothing but by <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> liſtened to her, took Fire, and his Love making uſe of a ſentiment of Ambition, for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing from him the baſe and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile complaiſance he had for a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he reſolved with her to attack <hi>Sigebert,</hi> in hopes of ſuddenly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering his Territories. Whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on he raiſed Forces ſecretly, and marched himſelf at their Head, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied by <hi>Meroveus,</hi> towards <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> after having left the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of all Affairs to <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> went not to this Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition without regret, becauſe he naturally hated Injuſtice: and he alſo made appear, he only fought for Peace, and did but ſhew his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the preparing the two Kings to a Reconciliation. The Army came in a few days to the Walls of <hi>Rheims,</hi> which after having main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſome Aſſaults, was at length conſtrained to open its Gates, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:33895:25"/>ſuffer the victorious Enemy to come in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigebert</hi> was acquainted ſome days after with this ſad News, and was obliged, as we have already ſaid, to make Peace with the <hi>Huns.</hi> He ſent immediately to <hi>Gontran,</hi> to give him notice of this ſurprize, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire his Aid to defend himſelf againſt <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s Treachery. He likewiſe ſent to demand Succours of <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gildus,</hi> King of the <hi>Goths</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> to whom he had formerly given the like againſt <hi>Agila,</hi> King of the <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goths. Athanagildus,</hi> in whom ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices made a great impreſſion, did not ſtick to acknowledge thoſe that <hi>Sigebert</hi> had done him, and was willing to go ſuccour him in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: After having ſetled his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and truſted the Conduct of them in Perſons he judged the moſt capable, as it was a very uſual thing to the Kings of that time, to carry with them their Wives and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, he marched out of his Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:33895:25"/>with a very powerful Army, accompanied with the Queen, and the two Princeſſes his Daughters.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Sigebert</hi> return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed towards <hi>Rheims,</hi> in all haſte, of which he became Maſter in a few days: <hi>Chilperick,</hi> who was gone from thence, having left in it but a weak Garriſon. The King of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraſia</hi> was not contented with ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving recovered that place; it was his turn, he thought, to make ſome attempts upon his Enemies Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. He went and attacqued him in <hi>Fiſmes,</hi> where he then was for the appeaſing ſome Sedition that was raiſed there; he preſſed him ſo vigorouſly, that <hi>Chilperick</hi> quickly ſaw himſelf in a condition of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring his Clemency, rather than irritating his valour: Wherefore he had recourſe to <hi>Gontran,</hi> to ſoften him in his Favour. <hi>Gontran</hi> was arrived a little time before in <hi>Sige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s Camp: as Peace and Union were the only things he breathed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:33895:26"/>he favourably heard the perſons <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick</hi> ſent him, and made ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to <hi>Sigebert,</hi> that he obliged him to compoſe with his Brother, and to that effect to make a ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Arms. There was an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of theſe three Princes, and through <hi>Gontran's</hi> interceſſion, the Peace was at length concluded, and publiſhed. The truth is, it was ſomething a ſhameful one for <hi>Chilpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick;</hi> but ſuch as he merited.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Athanagildus</hi> approaching nearer and nearer, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving learn'd this reconciliation, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſed the beſt part of his Troops, but upon the Princes deſire he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced towards them with his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. They ſent the Principal Lords of their Court to meet him, and received him in the Palace with great marks of eſteem and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. <hi>Sigebert,</hi> above all, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly thanked him for the part he had taken in his Intereſts. There were ſeveral gallant Feaſts made, of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:33895:26"/>which <hi>Brunchaut</hi> and <hi>Galſuinta</hi> were ever the greateſt Ornaments. Sports, Shows and Treats reigned then in all their luſtre, and never did any Court, compoſed of ſo many Kings, appear ſo neat and ſo magnificent.</p>
               <p>While that ſo ſweet a Calm en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted all their minds, and that they all ſtrove to diſſipate, in ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Divertiſements, the troubles and alarms of War; Love, being willing to contribute to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe Princes, fancied that ſo tranquil pleaſures were not touching enough, and that for the augmenting their force, he ought to mingle with them ſome of his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s indifference had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways appeared to him injurious to his Glory, inſomuch that he reſolved to revenge himſelf in that occaſion, but he would make him at the ſame time find that that liberty that an inſenſible heart does ſometimes va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue it ſelf for, is but an imaginary good, and that it is neceſſary to feel
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:33895:27"/>the effects of ſo fair a paſſion, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a perfect felicity.</p>
               <p>Nothing can be imagined more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed, than this Princeſs was, at that time when ſhe was ſeen &amp; heard to ſpeak, it was not known which one ought moſt to admire in her, her Beauty or her Wit. The ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing luſtre of her Face did ſo ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance the Charms of her Diſcourſe, that a heart remained ſuſpended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe two Objects, and it would have been difficult to ſay, which made it the ſooneſt ſigh. <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebert</hi> at each look ſhe fixed upon him, and at each word ſhe uttered, felt a flaming Dart which penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into his Soul, and inflamed all his Deſires. His paſſion was too fair, and his Vows too well placed to diſſemble them. After having aſſured himſelf of <hi>Brunchauts</hi> heart, who according to the cuſtom of young Women only ſighed for a Throne, he ſpake thereof to <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gildus.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:33895:27"/>
               <p>The King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the ſingular eſteem he had for the King of <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> was very glad to procure powerful Allies, hearkned to him with all poſſible favour, and after having communicated it to the Queen his Wife, and to ſome perſons of his Council, he made him a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive anſwer, and gave him his word for that Marriage.</p>
               <p>As all theſe Princes were willing to return, each one to his State, the preparations for this Nuptial pomp were made with all ſpeed, but it was not the leſs ſplendid; and it appear'd that thoſe who had had the managing of it, had foreſeen at firſt, that on one and the ſame day would be made a double Feaſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gontran</hi> had learnt with a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſpleaſure <hi>Chilperick's</hi> divorce from <hi>Andouera;</hi> and as the glory of his Blood was dear to him, he could not ſuffer that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> ſhould mount upon his Brothers Throne, by ſo unjuſt and ſhameful means.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:33895:28"/>Seeing that it would have been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt impoſſible to have re-eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Andouera,</hi> he bethought himſelf of another expedient, which might in ſome manner repair <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s Crime, which was to make him marry <hi>Galſuinta, Brunchauts</hi> Siſter, imagining that the luſtre of the Blood, and likewiſe of the Vertues of that Princeſs, might deface the Stain wherewith ſo unhappy a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had newly ſtained his Brother. He acquainted <hi>Sigebert</hi> with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and told him, that they both ought to intereſs themſelves in this affair, and not to let ſo favourable an occaſion eſcape.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigebert,</hi> whoſe inclinations were conformable to his Brothers, was of his opinion: they went together to find out <hi>Chilperick,</hi> and remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to him that Kings Marriages ought to be the effect of a wiſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and not of a blind paſſion, that when he was to aſſociate a Woman to his Throne, he ought only to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:33895:28"/>conſult the good of the State, and that the heart ought not to have any part in it, that he did not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely blame him for having put a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>Andouera,</hi> ſince that alliance had been very uſeleſs to him, but that he ought to make choice, in her place, of an illuſtrious perſon, and who might bring into his Intereſts the Princes of her Blood; that for the ſetling and cementing the Peace they had newly ſworn, it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient he ſhould marry the Princeſs <hi>Galſuinta;</hi> that it would be the means to ſtifle, by ſo near an union, all the difference that might ariſe in the future between the two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; In fine, if he was deſirous their Reconciliation ſhould be intire, he muſt reſolve on that Marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick</hi> being of a ſoft and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful nature, durſt not reſiſt the Princes propoſitions; he conſented they ſhould agree the Affair with the King of the <hi>Goths,</hi> and promiſed to ratifie all they ſhould do.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:33895:29"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Athanagildus</hi> was over-joyed with this ſecond Alliance; but a ſcruple troubled him in favour of his Daughter, and he could not defend himſelf againſt the alarms that <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick</hi>'s love for <hi>Fredegonda</hi> gave him: Inſomuch that this Prince was obliged to ſwear upon the Altars, that <hi>Galſuinta</hi> ſhould be hence-forward the only object of his paſſion, and that he would wholly ſtifle the tenderneſs he had had for his favourite: a frivolous Oath, which he quickly fancied Love might diſpence him from.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Meroveus,</hi> in the midſt of ſo much publick rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, had his Soul alone delivered up to grief and ſadneſs. The Queen his Mothers misfortune, and <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonda</hi>'s happineſs, had rendred him uncapable of any ſentiments of joy: but he was not inſenſible of it when he learn'd, that a Princeſs was going to poſſeſs the place deſigned for his Enemy; and if a change ſo favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:33895:29"/>and ſo little hoped, could not wholly extinguiſh his reſentment, at leaſt he received no ſmall comfort to ſee <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s deſigns brought to nothing, in the moment ſhe fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied ſhe was above the capriciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fortune. He made <hi>Galſuinta</hi> ſeveral Viſits, and always made ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to her, with ſincere proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the deſire he had to ſee her reign with his Father. He went al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to ſee <hi>Brunchaut</hi> from time to time, and had with her ſeveral par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular conferences, in which he was never wearied with admiring her Beauty, and the extraordinary Charms of her Wit, but it was ever without trouble and emotion: the fatal hour not being yet come, that Love would employ that fair one for the ruine of this young Prince.</p>
               <p>Theſe Nuptials being celebrated with all manner of magnificence, they all returned towards their States. <hi>Athanagildus</hi> went towards <hi>Spain; Gontran</hi> towards <hi>Orleans;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:33895:30"/>Sigebert</hi> with <hi>Brunchaut</hi> took the way of <hi>Auſtraſia;</hi> and all the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees of <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s Court, obliged him to return to <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> to make, in the Capital of his Kingdom, a Triumphant entry with his new Bride.</p>
               <p>It muſt be avowed that Love is ſomething very capricious, that this fierce Tyrant of Souls is extream jealous of his Power and his Rights.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galſuinta</hi> had ſo lively and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Beauty, that no body could ſupport the luſtre of it without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement; and to give a perfect Idea of her, it is ſufficient to ſay that ſhe was an exact portraict of her Siſter <hi>Brunchaut.</hi> But though all the Graces ſhould have transformed themſelves into her, though Nature ſhould have drained it ſelf in forming her, <hi>Chilperick</hi> had married her with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out conſulting Love, and this was enough to make him conceive for her ſentiments of contempt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. Thoſe ſweet eagerneſſes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:33895:30"/>which uſually follow the firſt days of Marriage, and which appear with ſo much the more violence, in that they are often as the Tombs of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thoſe paſſionate tranſports, thoſe impatient deſires, thoſe troubles ever new, thoſe charming diſquiets, in fine, all that a heart ought to be ſenſible of, in the firſt moments of the poſſeſſion of what it loves, all this was unknown to <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s; and if he ſighed near the Princeſs, it was for regret of not being able to keep his word with <hi>Fredegonda.</hi> The domineering Charms of that Maid came every moment into his imagination; they were as a Vail, which hid from him <hi>Galſuinta</hi>'s Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; and if it happened by chance that he diſcovered ſome of them, they only helped to ſet off thoſe of <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> and to put that unhappy Prince in mind, that ſhe poſſeſſed them with much more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. In the midſt of his Court, he ſeemed to be in a vaſt ſolitude,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:33895:31"/>and his vexations, and his mortal fears, were the only Objects which took up his Soul. The more he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> his toruble and his diſquiets were the more encreaſed: but how horrible ſoever the torment was he ſuffered in this cruel agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he could have wiſhed to have remained eternally in it. He alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy repreſented to himſelf <hi>Fredegon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> who with thoſe imperious words which ſhe was uſed to make uſe of in her reſentments, came to aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate him with reproaches, accuſed him of weakneſs, and ſwore to him an irreconcileable hatred. And it muſt likewiſe be avowed, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing has ever equalled the vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that ambitious Woman, and that as ſoon as ſhe had received the news of this Marriage, ſhe abandoned her ſelf to all the ſentiments of rage and deſpair that a woman can be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of.</p>
               <p>Some days before <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rival, ſhe pretended to be ſick, that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:33895:31"/>ſhe might not be obliged to go ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reſpects and ſubmiſſions to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whom ſhe could hardly ſupport the ſight of, without dying for grief.</p>
               <p>In fine, that great day being come that the King entred <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> after having received there, with the new Queen, all the honours that Subjects uſe to do their Princes in ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, he retired into his Palace, where having immediately asked for <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> he was told ſhe was very ſick. This news gave him the more boldneſs to ſee her, but on the other ſide it ſtrangely alarm'd him. He ſtole from <hi>Galſuinta,</hi> while that flocks of people invironed her, and ran all tranſported to <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as ſhe perceived the King and that ſhe had obſerved in his Eves and his Face, the Empire ſhe had ſtill over his heart, ſhe prevented him, and told him that ſhe foreſaw, that the Diſeaſe ſhe laboured under would carry her to her Grave; but that ſhe ſhould enter it with joy, ſince
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:33895:32"/>ſhe was precipitated into it by the exceſs of her love: that however ſhe ſhould have dyed more content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if her virtue had permitted her to have given him more ſenſible marks of her paſſion.</p>
               <p>Nothing is more ſurprizing to a Lover, than to hear kind things, and flatteries, from his Miſtreſſes mouth, when he expected nothing but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches and threatnings, neither is there any thing more capable of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him deteſt his infidelity, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire him with more love.</p>
               <p>This flattering and artificious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> ſo moved <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick,</hi> that all the powers of his Soul remained a long time in diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. He had ſo little force left, that he had recourſe to his ſighs, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to ſome tears, for the explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Miſtreſs the deſpair her illneſs reduced him to. Striving at length to ſpeak to her, he begged of her not to renounce life, and ſwore to her, that if ſhe would promiſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:33895:32"/>him to take care of it, he would put her, notwithſtanding the preſent conjuncture, in a ſtate in a ſhort time of reconciling her glory with her Love. He was not willing to ſtay any longer with her that day, leſt all his Court ſhould know he was ſtill in love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> then recovered firm hopes of mounting upon the Throne, and as the reputation of <hi>Galſuinta</hi>'s Beauty and Merit, made her appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the King might become inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly charmed, ſhe reſolved to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch that Princeſs as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhe could. But becauſe ſhe would be preſent her ſelf, at that fatal execution, for the making it the more ſure, ſhe was obliged to wait ſometime, for fear her ſickneſs ſhould be diſcovered to have been feigned, if ſhe quitted her Bed all of a ſudden. In the Viſits that the King dayly made her, ſhe aſſured him that ſhe grew better and better, and that the obliging words he had
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:33895:33"/>ſaid to her, had been more healing than all the remedies of the world.</p>
               <p>In fine, the certainty of her reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very being ſpread through all the Palace, after having prepared her ſelf for that horrible Sacrifice, ſhe went one day to make the Queen a Viſit; and choſe the time that ſhe was only attended by two of her Maids of Honour. The two Guards that were placed at her Chamber Door were <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Creatures. Some mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents after her being there, a young Man to whom ſhe had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed great Favours, came likewiſe thither, and coming briskly up to the Queen, he on a ſudden plunged his Dagger into her Breaſt, and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that unfortun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Princeſs to fall at his F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. <hi>Fredegonda</hi> thereupon feigning a great ſurprize, cryed out like mad, that they ſhould ſeize the Murderer; the two Guards running into the Chamber ſeized him, and cut him to pieces, according to the order ſhe had given them, for fear
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:33895:33"/>that the Rack and remorſe might make that Wretch tell what moved him to ſo deteſtable a Parricide; ſo true it is, that great Ones, who make uſe of other men to execute their pernicious Deſigns, often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve at the ſame time to ſacrifice them alſo to themſelves, that the death of theſe blind Miniſters may ſerve for a Vail and Cloud to their Deſigns.</p>
               <p>The noiſe of this Tragical Death being ſpread through all the Palace, the King run to ſee this pitiful Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle. Though he did not love <hi>Galſuinta,</hi> and that by the irregula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his paſſion, there aroſe in his Soul, I know not what malign Joy, in that he ſaw a perſon ſo conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently diſpatched, who traverſed his happineſs; however the innocence of that fair Queen, her Blood all ſmoaking, which came in great Floods from her Wound, her Boſom which ſeemed ſtill to heave; in fine, her Eyes which ſeemed to recollect
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:33895:34"/>their greateſt luſtre, before they clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever, objects ſo tender and ſo touching, excited in his heart a ſtrong pity, and a juſt reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the Aſſaſſinate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> would make him know that ſhe was no leſs ſenſible than he for this misfortune; ſhe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſhed Tears, but it was rather for joy than grief. Yet as there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more natural than to let our ſelves be perſuaded by thoſe we love, <hi>Chilperick</hi> fancyed ſhe was innocent, and that ſhe had not had any part in the murder.</p>
               <p>A Tomb was erected for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and <hi>Fredegonda</hi> to take away all ſuſpicion was careful it ſhould be the moſt glorious of all thoſe that had yet appeared. She affected at <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuinta</hi>'s Funeral, all the regrets that are uſual to perſons really afflicted. But the clear-ſighted did not fail to diſcover, through this diſguiſe, that it was ſhe who had cauſed her death; and her Marriage with the King,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:33895:34"/>which was celebrated ſome ſhort time after, opening the Eyes of the moſt credulous, inſpired in all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſentiments of hatred and indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation againſt her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> eſpecially to whom her new Dignity, and the Death of the Princeſs, were equally ſenſible, fell into a kind of rage againſt her: he reſolved to be revenged at the peril not only of his Life, but even of that of the Queen his Mother, who ſtill led, at <hi>Mans,</hi> a languiſhing and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Life.</p>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Fredegonda</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending that <hi>Sigebert,</hi> doubting of the truth, would revenge the Death of his Siſter in Law, inſtead of <hi>Athanagildus,</hi> whom a Feaver had lately taken out of this World; wherefore ſhe bethought her ſelf of preventing him. And thereupon remonſtrated to the King that it was of the utmoſt importance to make reflexion upon the conſequences that <hi>Galſuinta</hi>'s death might have
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:33895:35"/>that the malignity of Men made them often treat as criminal the moſt innocent actions upon the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances; that ſhe already foreſaw that her Marriage would eſtabliſh in baſe minds, a firm belief, that ſhe had cauſed that attempt; that theſe falſe reports making a ſtrong impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on the minds of <hi>Sigebert</hi> and his Miniſters, he would not fail to form the Deſign of attacquing him; that the remembrance of their paſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences would be a powerful Spur to excite his vengeance; In fine, that it was policy and prudence to prevent him and not to ſtay till he came and over-run their Territories with a powerful Army.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick</hi> whoſe blind paſſion had made him forget the misfortune that <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s councels had plunged him into, did not ballance to follow her ſentiments: He cauſed his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to aſſemble, but it was only to keep a vain formality. The War againſt <hi>Sigebert</hi> was there reſolved
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:33895:35"/>on notwithſtanding the opinions of thoſe of beſt ſenſe; and on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Orders were given for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Forces, and to be in a poſture of marching with the ſooneſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="57-115" type="pages">
               <p>The preparations of this War be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made, <hi>Fredegonda</hi> was willing to go to it in perſon, for the anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Kings courage; and to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from making any Peace with his Brother; She prayed him to leave <hi>Meroveus</hi> at <hi>Soiſſons. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick</hi> granted that willingly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew that this young Prince had ill intentions againſt his Mother-in-Law, and was likewiſe very willing to confide the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Affairs in a perſon of Name and Authority. Wherefore he ordered his Son to be careful in his abſence of the neceſſities of his State, and made him in that Place Depoſiter of his Almightineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> received this Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion both with joy and diſpleaſure. As he knew the injuſtice of that War,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33895:36"/>he was very glad to ſee himſelf di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſed from going to fight againſt perſons whoſe quarrel he would have run to imbrace, if nature had not oppoſed: but on the other ſide his reſentment was extream, when he conſidered that his Victim eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped him. The firſt conſideration, joyned to his Duty, prevailed how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever over his reſentment. He di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed himſelf to fill worthily <hi>Chilpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi>'s place, &amp; to make appear to the people that Fate was unjuſt to him in letting him be ſo long a Subject.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> ſeeing the Army quite ready, aſſigned her ſelf the day of departure, and obliged the King to it, who ſleeping in the boſom of a ſweet and ſoft idleneſs, did not quit without regret the Walls of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> ſhe mounted with him into a Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, wherein magnificence and lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ury made appear all that they had moſt ſplendid. The Army, which environed this proud pomp, march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſecond time towards <hi>Rheimes.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33895:36"/>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Sigebert</hi> was buſied with making head againſt the <hi>Huns,</hi> who were returned to thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der upon his Territories. He ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> already for ſome time been aſſured of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Crime, and he wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with impatience for the end of the War, to go and demand of <hi>Chilperick,</hi> Juſtice for ſo horrid an Attempt. But as ſoon as he was acquainted that he himſelf advanced with a great Army againſt him, he could not delay any longer his ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, and was willing to ſacrifice part of his Glory to ſo juſt a reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Wherefore he once more made Peace with the <hi>Huns,</hi> yielding up much more of his Intereſts than he would have done in another jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. He advanced with ſpeed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his Enemy, followed by ſixty thouſand <hi>Germans.</hi> The two Armies met near <hi>Rheimes,</hi> where there was a terrible Checque, but Fortune contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to its cuſtom favoured the juſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Party. She made in a little time the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:33895:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:33895:37"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:33895:38"/>incline on <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s ſide. All <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s Army was put to the Rout. That wretched King having rallied ſome Troops, fled with <hi>Fredegonda</hi> to <hi>Tournay,</hi> that they might not fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hands of the Conquerour.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gontran</hi> having learn'd the fatal ſucceſs of this Battel, could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear having ſome ſenſe of pity for <hi>Chilperick,</hi> though he had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore odious to him for all the crimes which his Love for <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had again ſtained him with. He was willing to be a ſecond time the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator of a Peace betwixt his two Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; wherefore he uſed all his efforts to make the King of <hi>Auſtraſia</hi> agree to it, on whom it depended.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigebert</hi> whoſe heart was great and generous, ſeemed at firſt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline to his Prayers: but it is ſo dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult, even to the faireſt Souls, to ſtop on a ſudden the courſe of their Paſſions, and ſtifle all the motions of a legitimate vengeance, that this Prince ſilenced his clemency, for to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:33895:38"/>exerciſe the ſeverity of his juſtice. He heard the cryes of all his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who could not ſuffer to be ſtopped in the midſt of their carreer; and he liſtned more than to the cryes of his Souldiers, to ſentiments of ambition which now and then roſe in his heart. Wherefore he made known to <hi>Gontran,</hi> that he could not conſent to what he exacted from him, ſince that it was but too juſt that <hi>Chilperick</hi> ſhould be puniſhed for his Treachery. He went to <hi>Paris,</hi> which opened to him its Gates, and wherein he entred victorious and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing. Queen <hi>Brunchaut</hi> his Wife came thither likewiſe, after which he thought of going to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue his Enemy. The Queen at his departure earneſtly conjured him not to ſpare <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> which he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly promiſed her. He went im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately to encamp at <hi>Vitry,</hi> where all the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtrian</hi> Lords coming to him, made Oath of Fidelity to him, acknowledged him for their King,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:33895:39"/>and Crowned him. After which he marched towards <hi>Tournay,</hi> which he quickly brought to extremity by a preſſing Siege. <hi>Chilperick,</hi> wholly terrified, waited only for the fatal hour that was to deliver him into his Enemies hands, when he ſaw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a moment ſecured from the danger that threatned him, by a Crime worthy of <hi>Fredegonda.</hi> That cunning Woman might that day brag ſhe had ſatisfied him for all the ills ſhe had made him ſuffer. She ſo well knew how to gain by her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, two Inhabitants of the City, that they offered themſelves to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake blindly what ſhe exacted from them. Whereupon they found the means of going into the Beſiegers Camp, where they asked to ſee <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gebert,</hi> for the communicating to him a Deſign of great importance. The Guards by an imprudence, which is pretty uſual in ſuch encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, introduced them into his Tent. As ſoon as the Murderers perceived
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:33895:39"/>that unfortunate Prince, they fell furiouſly upon him, and each of them gave him two ſtabs with their Daggers, of which he dyed immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</p>
               <p>This Parricide was hardly execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, than that all the Beſiegers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken with a mortal fear, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an unexpreſſible conſternation. They thought of nothing more than the imploring the Mercy of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged, and this Camp wherein joy was ſo generally ſpread, appeared only then a fatal Stage of deſpair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick</hi> and <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> ſeeing their Fate changed in an inſtant by ſo favourable a reverſe, went out of the City in Triumph. They return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all ſpeed towards <hi>Paris,</hi> where, upon the report of <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s Death, <hi>Brunchaut</hi> had been ſecured to be delivered to them. <hi>Fredegon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> would have had her loſt her Life. but <hi>Chilperick</hi> once wanted that complaiſance, and contented himſelf with baniſhing that unfortunate
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:33895:40"/>Princeſs to <hi>Roan.</hi> After having cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Meroveus</hi> to come to him, he ſent him to take poſſeſſion of <hi>Poitou,</hi> which made part of <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>This young Prince had learn'd the death of the King of <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> with all the grief and all the regrets that can be expected from a perſon who hates injuſtice. This new Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, of which he was Heir, had not Charms enough to flatter his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he never had a thought unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming his Virtue and his Glory. That which moſt ſharpned his grief, was the Commiſſion that the King gave him, which would in ſome manner render him an Accomplice of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Crimes. Wherefore he could never reſolve to execute it. He had however ſo much command o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf as to diſſemble before <hi>Chilperick.</hi> He took leave of him to go into <hi>Poitou:</hi> but, after having tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled ſome dayes, he left that Road to go to <hi>Mans.</hi> He was willing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:33895:40"/>once more to ſpeak to his Mother, and injoy before her Death the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of that good Princeſs. The ſight of <hi>Meroveus</hi> cauſed in her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credible tranſports and extaſies. She made them appear by her Tears and her Sighs, that were the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes that ſhe held with him. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having entertained themſelves with their misfortunes, and of what they had to do, they were to part. As <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had the Title of Queen, <hi>Andouera</hi> thought it unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming her Virtue to diſpatch her by cunning and baſe means. She did not believe that all the Crimes of that wicked Woman, could au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſe an action that ſhould have any reſemblance with hers. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe propoſed to the Prince to go ſee <hi>Brunchaut</hi> for to confer with her, and to engage, by her means, the greateſt Men of <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <hi>Fredegonda</hi> of <hi>Chilperick,</hi> to ſacrifice her to their King, and upon his refuſal, ſhould make War upon
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:33895:41"/>him, whoſe ſucceſs would be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps more happy than it had been.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> conſented with joy to this propoſition, and took leave of the Princeſs. It ſeem'd at their part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that <hi>Andouera</hi> had a ſecret pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of her Son's misfortune: a great ſhivering went through all her Body, her fancy was filled with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal objects, and her tears were dryed up, as too weak to expreſs the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of her grief, ſhe embraced the Prince ſeveral times, and felt her ſelf fixed to him by ſomething more ſtrong and more extraordinary than the tenderneſſes of Blood. In fine, <hi>Meroveus</hi> having forced himſelf from her Arms, as againſt her Will, he immediately left <hi>Mans</hi> to go in all ſpeed to <hi>Roan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It was there that Love and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune expected this young Prince, to make him ſenſible of all that they have moſt cruel, and to perfect his ruine, which they had conſpired to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:33895:41"/>
               <p>In all the way he felt himſelf agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated with an unknown trouble, and which he could not attribute to any of the paſſions he had felt. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having been received in <hi>Roan</hi> with all the illuſtrious marks of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that were due to his quality and his merit, he would go make a viſit to <hi>Brunchaut.</hi> The nearer he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached the place where ſhe was, the more his trouble and his agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions encreaſed. By a very capri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious effect two contrary motions led him on and ſtopped him at the ſame time. In fine, that ſecret timi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity ſuffering him to do his Devoir, he entred the Princeſſes Chamber, whom he found plunged into a deep melancholy.</p>
               <p>Of all the Darts of Love, there are none whoſe ſtroaks we receive with leſs reſiſtance than thoſe which iſſue from the misfortunes of the perſon we are to love. The affection of a fair one is ſo touching a Charm to a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous heart, that it is almoſt impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:33895:42"/>for it to intereſs it ſelf in her Fate, by the ſole ſentiments of pity. The Soul ſoftned by ſo ſad an object, eaſily forgets it ſelf to conſider it on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: its deſires are ſtirred up, its powers are in motion, and in the midſt of this diſorder I know not what kind of languiſhing, mingled with grief and diſpleaſure together, penetrates all its foldings.</p>
               <p>If it was a happineſs for <hi>Brunchaut</hi> to be beloved by <hi>Meroveus,</hi> it may be ſaid the ſtate ſhe was then redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to, was the greateſt favour ſhe had received from Fortune. Her Eyes through Rivers of Tears which run inceſſantly, ſent fearful and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing looks to the Prince, which immediately found an eaſie paſſage to his very heart: The paleneſs and alteration of her Face did not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the admiring ſtill thoſe ſecret Graces, which procured her as many Adorers, as there were perſons who approached her. It even ſeemed that Love for the better ſecuring his
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:33895:42"/>Conqueſt, had raiſed the luſtre of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> was a long time mute before her, and only anſwered her Tears with his Sighs. <hi>Brunchaut</hi> took his ſadneſs and ſilence for an ill augure. She fancyed that he came to execute ſome fatal ſentence that <hi>Chilperick,</hi> or rather <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> had pronounced againſt her; that the ſight and Idea of her miſeries touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the young Prince: but that his generoſity and compaſſion, would not be cap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of over-coming the obedience he owed the King his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; inſomuch that ſhe thought of nothing elſe than of preparing her ſelf for Death. After having ſtrove to ſtop for ſome moments the courſe of her Tears, ſhe told the Prince, ſighing, that amongſt all the ills ſhe had foreſeen, ſhe had never expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the utmoſt rigour of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, what it was going to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her; that ſhe perceived her fatal hour was come; that ſhe had
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:33895:43"/>courage enough not to murmur at it, and to go without regret to find out her Husband in the Grave: But that ſhe could not ſuffer without complaining, that a Prince whom ſhe had ever eſteemed for his Virtue, ſhould have charged himſelf with the care of her Death; that ſhe was but too well aſſured of it, by thoſe marks even of pity that he gave her, and that he made it enough known by his ſilence that it was all that he could grant her.</p>
               <p>This reproach quite oppreſs'd <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus,</hi> it put him entirely out of a condition of explaining his ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to <hi>Brunchaut:</hi> Nothing but his Eyes had been able to have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered ſomething to her, if ſhe had well conſulted them. The new trouble ſhe obſerved in his Face con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed her in the errour ſhe was in. She perſuaded her ſelf that the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexity ſhe ſaw this Prince in, was a tacite confeſſion of all ſhe had ſaid to him; when ſhe made a ſtrong re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:33895:43"/>upon her misfortunes, the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of her grief made her fall into a ſwoon. Her Maids who retired out of reſpect, run all in at the noiſe they heard, and brought her to her ſelf again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> received the firſt glan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of her Eyes half open. His ſighs then permitting him to break a ſilence, that had been ſo injurious to her, he told the Princeſs that ſhe was very cruel and unjuſt to have ſuch low thoughts of him; that no deſign was formed againſt her, that the deſire only of ſeeing her had brought him to <hi>Roan:</hi> But though that <hi>Chilperick</hi> and <hi>Fredegonda</hi> ſhould have conſpired her ruine, he would not ballance to embrace her defence againſt them; that he was not only animated to it by his Glory and his Virtue, that he found himſelf tyed to her by Bonds much more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful than thoſe of Nature, that ſhe ought not to attribute to his pity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, the fatal eſtate her ſight had
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:33895:44"/>reduced him to; that nothing but ſo ſtrong a paſſion as Love was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of producing ſo ſtrange effects; that he was reſolved to procure her her liberty, even at the peril of his Life; that he would not force her heart to any acknowledgment for his Services; but that if without doing violence to her inclinations ſhe could ſuffer his Vows, he prayed her to favour them, and conſent to the happineſs of a Prince who might one day make her reign upon the chiefeſt Throne of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunchaut</hi> was ſo ſurprized with ſo unexpected a diſcourſe, that the exceſs of joy made almoſt in her the ſame effect that grief had done. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter having remained a long time mute, ſhe anſwered the Prince that ſhe ſhould be very credulous to add faith to his words, the preſent jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture of affairs little permitting them to think of ſuch a deſign; but that if he would give her real marks of his Love, he ought to endeavour her
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:33895:44"/>liberty, as he had newly promiſed her; that they might afterwards ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe more at leiſure, of what would be convenient for them to do, for both their repoſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> too much reſpected the Princeſſes will to contradict it: he even ſtole away from the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, that he ſhould have reliſhed in a longer converſation, to run and give her marks of his obedience and his zeal. He ſent for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of the Caſtle the Princeſs was in, and told him that he deſired ſhe ſhould go out and be at liberty, that he would be reſponſible, the King ſhould not take it ill, and that he would charge himſelf with his Conduct. This Officer too much reſpected his Kings eldeſt Son, not to conſent to what he demanded, he preſented him with the Keys of the Caſtle, and told him that he might uſe them as he ſhould think fit.</p>
               <p>A reflexion which came into <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi>'s
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:33895:45"/>mind, hindered him from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning then to the Princeſs. Never had any fair paſſion in a great heart been ſo violent in ſo little a time as this was. It ſeemed as if Love had only ſpared him till then for the making him feel at once all the tranſports that can agitate a Lover, during ſeveral years. The poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Brunchaut</hi> appeared to him ſo perfect a happineſs, that it is not to be wondred, if he thought more of ſecuring that than any thing elſe. By a motion of diſtruſt, very uſual to Lovers, he apprehended that the Princeſs once releaſed out of Priſon, would immediately vaniſh out of his ſight; wherefore he fancyed that he ought, before all things, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy all his efforts to get her conſent to their Marriage.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he went to ſee her the next day: The ſight of her did not cauſe in him any new encreaſe of Love, his paſſion being uncapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of receiving any. He told her
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:33895:45"/>he had found the Captain of the Guards inflexible to his Prayers; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat that Officer durſt not diſpoſe of any thing without expreſs Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders from Court; but upon his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving aſſured him, that he would publickly marry the Princeſs as ſoon as ever ſhe was ſet free, he had made known to him he would favour his Deſign; that ſhe could not then recover her liberty but at that rate; that, ſince time preſſed, ſhe ought to declare her ſelf with the ſooneſt, and to examine her ſelf if it was not more advantageous for her to enter into Sacred Bonds with a Prince, who would make it eternally all his happineſs to pleaſe her, than to languiſh ſadly in an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure Priſon.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Meroveus</hi> ſhould have dived into all the moſt ſecret thoughts of <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> he could not more agreeably have flattered her deſires. She had made ſeveral re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexions upon the firſt viſit of this
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:33895:46"/>Prince. As ſhe had apprehended his Love was only a paſſing flame, which would be the more eaſily extinguiſhed, in that it had appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at firſt with too much violence, ſhe was diſpleaſed with her ſelf that ſhe had not made better uſe of the occaſion, for the deeper en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging him, and that ſhe had too exactly obſerved ſcrupulous decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies out of ſeaſon. She had conſidered that ſhe could not find a firmer ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port againſt the hatred of <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> her mortal Enemy; that even <hi>Chilpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> could not diſpence himſelf from protecting her, when he ſaw her his Sons Wife; that her glory was intereſſed in this Alliance, ſince it was the higheſt Rank ſhe could then aſpire to. Neither was this young Prince ſo indifferent to her, but that Love made her give him the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereſt of her Vows. Wherefore ſhe told him that ſince ſhe ſaw her ſelf forced to open to him all her heart, liberty was not the greateſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:33895:46"/>good ſhe deſired; that ſhe ſhould even conſider it as the worſt of ills, if it only ſerved to abſent her from a perſon who could alone make her good or ill Fortune; that ſhe had been no leſs troubled at the ſight of the Prince, than he had been at hers; that in fine, the ſighs of two hearts were never ſo well met.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> whom this diſcourſe put into an extaſie, interrupted it, to make known to the Princeſs the tranſports of his joy, by all the terms that Love can put into the mouth of the moſt paſſionate Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. After which he told her ſhe muſt haſten ſo longed for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and endeavour without cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the eſtabliſhment of their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual happineſs; that he was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Archbiſhop, <hi>Pretextat,</hi> his God-father, to obtain from him the Diſpenſation that was neceſſary for them; that he did not believe he would refuſe it him, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:33895:47"/>received from that Prelate, in other rencounters, ſeveral marks of a particular affection.</p>
               <p>After theſe words he left her, and run to <hi>Pretextat</hi>'s houſe, to whom he communicated his Deſigns, praying him to bring no obſtacle to them.</p>
               <p>The Prelate ſtrangely ſurprized with ſuch a piece of News, remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated to the young Prince, that he better ought to command his paſſion and moderate his deſires; that what he demanded of him could not be done; that it would cauſe too great a ſcandal in the world; and that it would likewiſe expoſe them both to the Kings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment.</p>
               <p>This cruel refuſal reduced this poor Lover to deſpair: he begged and threatned by turns, but his prayers and his threatnings were equally in vain, and <hi>Pretextat,</hi> to avoid the ill effects they might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, left him angrily, and run to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:33895:47"/>ſhut himſelf up in the moſt ſecret place of the Houſe, <hi>Meroveus</hi> went away in ſuch furious tranſports that he was not himſelf. He went to <hi>Gailan</hi> his Confident, whom he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what he ſhould do in that ſad caſe, and that if he judged it not convenient to go ſeize the <hi>Pretex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat</hi> cunningly, for to frighten him, and conſtrain him to conſent to his Marriage with <hi>Brunchaut. Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> was a man of a ripe and ſetled judgment, who rather deplored the blindneſs of his Maſter than inclined to flatter his paſſion. He told him that he ought not to act with ſo much precipitation, in an Affair of that importance; that he ought to foreſee the ills he would bring upon himſelf; that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had already but too much imbittered the King againſt him, without gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him ſtill ſo juſt a ſubject of complaint.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> whoſe anger was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed at ſo free a diſcourſe, ſilenced
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33895:48"/>his Confident with furious threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings. He told him, that if he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened his heart to him, it was to learn what way he ſhould take to arrive at the poſſeſſion of what he loved, and not to know what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences his Love might have; that he had foreſeen them as well as himſelf, but that they allarmed him but little, that he ſhould eſteem himſelf too happy, let what would happen, if he once ſaw himſelf <hi>Brunchauts</hi> Husband; that, in fine, he forbid him upon pain of Life, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to make him the like remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances.</p>
               <p>The paſſion of this unfortunate Prince proceeded to ſuch an exceſs, that his great Soul, which had ever been capable of embracing ſo many things at once, was then wholly poſſeſſed with it, it remained in a kind of inſenſibility for all other objects, and it was not known if it was ſtill ſuſceptible of reaſon but in entertaining <hi>Brunchaut. Gailan</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:33895:48"/>perceiving that this Lover was not in a condition to reliſh any mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate counſel, fancied that the moſt uſeful ſervice that he could do him, was to facilitate to him the poſſeſſion of his Miſtreſs, ſince if he came to miſs of her, it was to be feared his deſpair might carry him to attempt ſomething againſt himſelf. After having asked him pardon for the boldneſs his zeal had made him take, he told him that the ſureſt means to move <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>textat,</hi> was not to uſe rigour and threatnings; that he ought on the contrary renew more and more to him his prayers and ſubmiſſions, and make known to him that if he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf inexorable, it would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibly coſt the Princes Life, that he only ſaw two objects capable of giving him repoſe, his Marriage with <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> or Death.</p>
               <p>What weakneſſes is not Love ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of making a heart guilty of? And what low ſentiments does it
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:33895:49"/>not inſpire it with?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> whom the fear of the greateſt dangers, nor even death before his Eyes, had ever been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to make him ſtoop to his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, embraces <hi>Gailan,</hi> and does himſelf beg his excuſe for his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. He returned immediately to <hi>Pretextat</hi>'s houſe, to whom he ſent up word, that he beſeeched him to hear him yet once more, and that he needed not to apprehend any thing from him.</p>
               <p>The Prelate loving this young Prince, was not inſenſible to his misfortune. He was willing to give him the ſatisfaction he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and expoſe himſelf once more to his ſight. He came to him, and obſerving in his Face a a little more tranquility than before, he asked him if he begun to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of his paſſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> viewing him with lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Eyes, replyed, that <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut</hi> reigned too ſoveraignly in his
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:33895:49"/>heart, to believe he could ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce her poſſeſſion; that this ſerenity which appeared in his Face, was rather a mark of his deſpair, than of the tranquility of his Soul; that before he abandoned himſelf entirely to it, he returned to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore his goodneſs; that <hi>Pretextat</hi> had his Life and his Fate in his hands, that as ſoon as he ſhould have aſſured him that he ought not to pretend to the marriage of the Princeſs, he would run to Death.</p>
               <p>This diſcourſe uttered with an action wholly paſſionate, ſo moved <hi>Pretextat,</hi> that he could hardly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſhedding tears. He begged the Prince to believe that he ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in his grief, and that it was not without regret that he found himſelf unable to grant what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
               <p>At theſe fatal words, <hi>Meroveus,</hi> ſeized-with a blind fury, drew his Sword, and would have run him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33895:50"/>through in that Prelate's ſight, if he had not been hindred.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pretextat,</hi> who really found by this action, that it concerned the Princes Life to marry him to <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut,</hi> told him, to re-aſſure him, that ſince he ſaw this Marriage was ſo important to him, he would not reſiſt it any longer; that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever as he would not do any thing againſt his conſcience, and which might diſpleaſe the Holy See, he was willing to conſult firſt the moſt underſtanding Divines of <hi>Roan,</hi> and that within three days at the fartheſt he would give him a poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive anſwer.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Meroveus,</hi> who, beſides the impatience of his Love, feared with reaſon ſome obſtacle on <hi>Chilpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi>'s and <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s part, was not ſatisfied with theſe promiſes. He would not go from <hi>Pretextat</hi>'s houſe till he had aſſured him he would go that moment to conſult ſuch perſons as were fit to clear his doubt.</p>
               <pb n="85" facs="tcp:33895:50"/>
               <p>In effect this Prelate loſt not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny time: He cauſed ſeveral Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors to aſſemble in all haſte, they all told him it was their opinion, he might celebrate the Princes Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage without wounding his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pretextat</hi> after having ſettled all on Gods ſide, was likewiſe wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to keep peace with the King as well as he could, or at leaſt to procure himſelf Defenders againſt his reſentment. Wherefore he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed this Alliance to the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable of the City, and told them that he would do nothing without their advice. <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s Crimes reflecting upon <hi>Chilperick,</hi> begun to render him as well as ſhe an object of hatred and contempt to all his Subjects. There was not one but looked with Eyes of pity upon <hi>Brunchaut</hi>'s Captivity: Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that <hi>Pretextat</hi> agreeably ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized all thoſe he ſpoke to of this Affair. Very far from oppoſing it,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:33895:51"/>they encouraged him to procure as ſoon as poſſible the happineſs of theſe Lovers, and vowed to him that they would ſecure him from the King and <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s anger, or that it ſhould coſt them their Lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pretextat,</hi> after ſo general a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, did not balance any longer. He ſought for <hi>Meroveus</hi> to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint him with this favourable News. This Prince whoſe paſſion was more and more irritated, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected with as much fear as impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience the ſentence that was to be given him. When he perceived <hi>Pretextat,</hi> he felt his Soul agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated with new allarms, his gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy curioſity was damped on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and he durſt not ask to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed of his Fate, imagining that he ſhould be too ſoon inſtructed with his misfortune. But as ſoon as the Prelate had aſſured him that all favoured his Deſigns, he caſt himſelf at his Feet, and vowed he
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:33895:51"/>would eternally remember the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice that he diſpoſed himſelf to do him: he prayed him to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the next morning for his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage with the Princeſs, and to be himſelf the ſacred Depoſitor of their mutual Oaths. <hi>Pretextat</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily granted him what he demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, inſomuch that the Prince up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this aſſurance left him, to go and give notice to his Miſtreſs of what paſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> who was already ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Prelates oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Meroveus</hi>'s deſires, was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly grieved at it: but when this Lover had pronounced to her their mutual happineſs, her Tears, with which her Face was all bathed, were dryed up in a moment, her griefs vaniſhed, and if there remained any trouble in her Soul, it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what Love and Joy excited there. During ſeveral hours that the Prince ſtayed with her, ardent ſighs and paſſionate looks, thoſe el<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>quent
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33895:52"/>Interpreters of the ſentiments of the heart, were even their principal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
               <p>Decency having at length part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe two Lovers, <hi>Meroveus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned home to paſs the reſt of the night. It was then that this Prince felt more than ever in his Soul thoſe uneaſie deſires, thoſe lively ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerneſſes, thoſe impatient tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, thoſe ſweet agitations ever blooming; In fine, all that an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourous heart can be ſenſible of, when itisi ſuddenly to poſſeſs what it loves.</p>
               <p>That ſo longed for hour being come, he returned to the Princeſſes Houſe, whom he told that it was time ſhe ſhould go out of Priſon, and that ſhe ought no longer to wear any other Chains than thoſe of Love.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> being willing to make the Empire ſhe had over <hi>Merove us,</hi> to further her Deſigns, viewed him with a ſad Eye, and which made it
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33895:52"/>apparent that there was ſomething wanting to her Vows.</p>
               <p>The Prince much ſtartled, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her to explain the ſubject of her grief. Whereupon ſhe made all the perſons retire who were in the Chamber, and told that Lover that ſince he had left her, ſhe had made a ſerious reflexion upon the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Affair ſhe was going to engage her ſelf in; that a ſecond Marriage ſo precipitated would in ſome manner wound her Glory; that this might make ſeveral be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that ſhe had been of intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence with <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s Murderers; that ſhe fancyed to have heard the Voice of that Husband, who cryed Vengeance to her, and reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her with her weakneſs and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
               <p>This Lover, to whom all theſe Words were as ſo many Darts
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:33895:53"/>piercing his Soul, interrupted the Princeſs, crying, that if ſhe was ſo cruel as ſolely to oppoſe his hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, by conſiderations meerly frivolous and chimerical, he would give himſelf, in her ſight, marks of his deſpair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> having prayed the Prince to hear her yet one moment, added to what ſhe had told him, that ſhe was too far ingaged to give back, and though ſhe could conſent to it, ſhe found that ſhe had not force enough over her ſelf, to hinder her from following the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of her heart; but that it was neceſſary that an illuſtrious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge ſhould juſtifie her carriage, and ſhould perſuade all people that ſhe would not have returned ſo ſoon to the Laws of Marriage, but for the better performing what ſhe owed to <hi>Sigebert</hi>'s Manes; that in fine, Victimes were required, and
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:33895:53"/>that before they went to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, ſhe exacted a faithful promiſe from him, that he would deliver to her ſuch as ſhe thought her due.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> anſwered <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> that her Will ſhould be eternally the only Rule of his Actions, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that he knew very well that in following them, he ſhould only follow what Glory would inſpire him with, whereupon putting a Fence to the ground, he took one of the Princeſſes hands, and ſwore he would ſacrifice to her ſuch Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims as ſhe ſhould think fit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided ſhe always excepted the King his Father.</p>
               <p>She told him that ſhe only aimed at <hi>Fredegonda</hi> and her Creatures: Inſomuch that theſe Lovers did eaſily reconcile all their ſentiments. They went from the Caſtle to the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:33895:54"/>Great Church where the Prelate ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected them. Never was Nuptial Pomp prepared with ſo much haſte, but one may ſay that it was more charming than all that Art or Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry had yet ſhewn, ſince Love ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in triumph there in its great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt luſtre.</p>
               <p>The crowd of people which run to ſee ſo fine a Sight, was ſo great, that the Souldiers could hardly make a free paſſage for the Chariot that carryed theſe Lovers; and the joy was ſo generally ſpread in all hearts, that all places ecchoed the Vows every one ſent to Heaven for their proſperity.</p>
               <p>That holy Ceremony being finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Prelate would treat the new marryed; he invited them to a Feaſt that he had cauſed to be prepared, with as much neatneſs and magnificence, as ſo ſhort a time
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:33895:54"/>could permit. Several of the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt perſons of the City were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of the Feaſt. They ſtrove with a kind of emulation to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliment this Royal Pair, and to teſtifie, eſpecially to <hi>Brunchaut,</hi> the extream diſpleaſure they had had in ſeeing her ſo unjuſtly languiſh in a hard Captivity. The Beauty of this Princeſs was then in its greateſt ſplendour; it ſeemed as if all the Graces were met in her; and there iſſued from her Eyes and her Face, I know not what luſtre, that had never been obſerved be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and wherein haughtineſs and ſweetneſs made together an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able mixture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> fixed all his looks up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her, and could not be ſatisfied with contemplating her; the more he ſaw her, the more new Charms did he diſcover; and though he had already formed a ſtrong Idea
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:33895:55"/>of them, he avowed in himſelf that the preſence of ſo rare an object effaced all that his imagination had repreſented to him in her abſence. He waited with an extream impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience for the end of that day, which ought to be the beginning of his happineſs, when that illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious company was told that <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick</hi> and <hi>Fredegonda</hi> were entred the City, followed by a Body of Horſe, and that ſeveral Squadrons were perceived at a diſtance coming on.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> as ſtruck with Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at that fatal News, remained a long time without motion. When he had recovered his Spirits, he did not doubt but that the King, animated by <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> would force the Houſe in which they were, and that his Mother-in-Law would uſe all her efforts to ruine <hi>Brunchaut.</hi> So that to preſerve a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:33895:55"/>Life that was much more dear to him than his own, he obliged the Princeſs to fly immediately away with him. Theſe two poor Lovers run to take refuge in the ſame Church, and at the Feet of the ſame Altars where they had newly entred into ſo holy Bonds.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick,</hi> notwithſtanding all that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> could ſay to him, durſt not draw them out by force; he was ſtill ſo much the Maſter of his reſentment, as not to violate the Sacred Aſile of all the unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. He ſent word to thoſe Lovers that they might come out with all ſafety, that being far from doing them any violence, he would rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie this Marriage, provided the Church conſented to it. How cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulous is Love, and how eaſily does it fall into the Snares that are laid for it? <hi>Brunchaut</hi> having ſtill pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence enough to foreſee what
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:33895:56"/>would happen, remonſtrated to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus,</hi> that they ought not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye on ſo ſuſpected and deceitful promiſes, and that <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s ſtrength lay ordinarily in Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Artifices.</p>
               <p>But this Lover, whom his paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on rendred no longer capable of any reflexion, told the Princeſs that this diſtruſt would only help to ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate the King, whoſe ſight they could not long avoid; that he hoped Nature would be ſtill ſo ſtrong in his Heart, as to overcome his reſentment.</p>
               <p>The too eaſie Princeſs yielded to the Prayers and Perſuaſions of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus.</hi> They both went to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver themſelves as unhappy Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctims into the hands of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>When they appeared before <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perick,</hi>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:33895:56"/>it was to no purpoſe their Tears ſpoke and raiſed the pity of all the People. This barbarous King, inſpired by his Wife, cauſed them inſtantly to be ſhut up in the Caſtle, but each in a Chamber a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; Inſomuch that the unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Brunchaut</hi> ſeemed to have breathed only ſome moments of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to be afterwards the more lively ſenſible of the rigours of her Priſon. Theſe Lovers were treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo much indignity, as that they were even refuſed the perſons whoſe ſervice was neceſſary to them. They were deprived of the conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they might have had in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating their thoughts, and in learning what was reſolved of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; In fine, ſuch as were obliged to come into their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, to carry them the neceſſaries of Life, were forbidden to ſpeak to them, and they had no other en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment than their Complaints.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:33895:57"/>
               <p>In the mean time <hi>Chilperick</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Pretextat</hi> to be ſeized, whom he accuſed of High Treaſon. For trying him he cauſed an Aſſembly of ſeveral other Prelates to be held, of whom the moſt part were the blind Miniſters of <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. <hi>Pretextat</hi> defended himſelf ſo couragiouſly, and by ſuch ſtrong reaſons, that his Judges, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging themſelves his innocence, had recourſe to Artifice to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn him. They remonſtrated to him, in ſecret, that this obſtinacy to defend himſelf would but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> more irritate the King, who would have him owe his ſafety to hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Clemency, and that as ſoon as h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhould ſee in him the marks of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubmiſſive Subject, he would ceaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to trouble him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pretextat</hi> ſuffered himſelf to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſeduced by theſe captious Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances. When that he returne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:33895:57"/>to the Aſſembly, he confeſſed before <hi>Chilperick</hi> the Crimes with which he was charged, and made himſelf, by this imprudent avowal, the Sentence of his Condemnation. For theſe words were hardly eſcaped from him, than that the King demand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed High Juſtice of the Prelates, and ſaid that the accuſed ought to be judged upon his Depoſition. Whereupon this innocent Wretch was immediately degraded, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to a little Deſart Iſland, near the City of <hi>Coutance,</hi> from whence af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a long Bondage he was at length re-called, and re-eſtabliſhed in his Dignity. But <hi>Fredegonda</hi> not knowing what it was to forget an injury, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be at laſt aſſaſſinated, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as he was celebrating Divine Service.</p>
               <p>That wicked Woman made uſe of all her Addreſſes and Power with the King, to oblige him to put <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:33895:58"/>and <hi>Meroveus</hi> to death. As ſhe ſaw that Nature was not yet whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly extinguiſhed in <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s heart, and that it did not permit him to ſhed ſo unjuſtly his own Blood, ſhe only demanded that of <hi>Brunchaut:</hi> But her hatred was deceived, and her Victime eſcaped from her when ſhe leaſt miſtruſted it.</p>
               <p>The Lords of <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> who yet knew nothing of what had paſſed, ſent Deputies to <hi>Chilperick</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demand of him their Queen, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate to him that they could not ſuffer ſhe ſhould be detained longer from them, without any reaſon; and that they were rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to implore Succours of all the neighbouring Princes, to procure ſatisfaction in this point. The Affair being ſeriouſly treated of in the Kings Council, this Demand was found ſo juſt and reaſonable, that, notwithſtanding all that <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>degonda</hi>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:33895:58"/>could ſay, it was reſolved that <hi>Brunchaut</hi> ſhould return unto her Territories, and ſhould depart with the Ambaſſadours. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhe was releaſed out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and <hi>Meroveus</hi> likewiſe out of his at the ſame time.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> in whom this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture cauſed tranſports of rage and deſpair, did all that ſhe could to moderate them by an imperfect vengeance, ſince that ſhe could not entirely exerciſe it. As it was impoſſible for her to find any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but in the unhappineſs of theſe Lovers, ſhe ordered they ſhould be releaſed together out of the Caſtle; and that they ſhould ſee one another once more; this cruel pleaſure ſhe only granted them that they might be the more lively ſenſible of their fatal ſeparation, and that they might have the Idea of it the more preſent.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:33895:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> fixing his looks upon the Princeſs, met with hers, which for the laſt time ſought the Princes heart, to explain to it her Love and her Grief. Never was a farewel ſo tender and ſo mourning: Seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral confuſed ſighs were almoſt the language that theſe Lovers held.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Brunchaut</hi> at length diſappearing from the Eyes of <hi>Meroveus,</hi> he was ſhut up in a Cloyſter, where, by a <hi>Capricio</hi> as fantaſtical as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, the King cauſed him to be ſhaved, and engaged him in the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders againſt his Will, believing thereby to deprive him of all means of ever intriguing in the World. A ſtrange and pernicious Policy of Men! who abuſe Religion e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the execution of their Crimes, and make uſe of the moſt Sacred Myſteries, as eaſie Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for their bringing to paſs their unjuſt enterprizes.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:33895:59"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chilperick,</hi> after having ſent <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut</hi> away, returned to <hi>Paris,</hi> with <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> and left his Son to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt at leiſure his vexations in his ſolitude.</p>
               <p>It was then that the heart of this Prince was wracked by allarms much more cruel than all thoſe with which he had been yet ſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and that he found himſelf agitated with all the other paſſions that are the uſual effects of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Love. When he thought how treacherouſly Fortune had dealt with him, that he conſidered that it had only brought him near his happineſs, to make his loſs of it the more ſenſible, he fell under his Grief. That charming Image of the Princeſſes Beauty that was ſo deeply impreſſed in his heart, and which inceſſantly offered it ſelf to his Eyes, did only help to encreaſe his ills, and augment his regrets.
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:33895:60"/>But his main trouble was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty he was in of <hi>Brunchaut</hi>'s Fate, and was in a mortal fear that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had cauſed her to be aſſaſſinated upon the Way. He could not conceive this Idea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſpair, and it was however what hindred him from attempting any thing himſelf, becauſe he would not abandon his Life, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured of that of the Princeſs. It was to no purpoſe he inquired News of her, all People were deaf to his Prayers, and the continual Favours that <hi>Fredegonda</hi> beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon that Houſe, ſtopped the mouths of all the Religious. He likewiſe tryed all manner of ways to eſcape from that place; but his endeavours were ſtill fruitleſs, till that his Enemy her ſelf facilitated to him the execution of this Deſign to compleat his ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredegonda</hi> had lately brought
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:33895:60"/>forth a Son to <hi>Chilperick,</hi> whom ſhe deſigned for the Throne, and fore-ſeeing that <hi>Meroveus,</hi> after the Kings Death, might return from his Vows with ſo much the more eaſe, in that his heart had e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver diſavowed them, ſhe fancyed that nothing but this Princes Death could ſecure the Crown to her Son: Wherefore ſhe reſolved of it, let what would happen. Of all the Creatures ſhe had made, the moſt powerful was <hi>Bozon,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-General of <hi>Sigebert's</hi> Armies. This man ſince the Death of that Prince had ever remained at <hi>Sige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi>'s Court, who conſidered him upon <hi>Fredegonda</hi>'s recommendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. She one day told this Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that ſhe muſt exact an impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Service from him, and that ſhe would fully acknowledge it. <hi>Bozon</hi> aſſured her that he was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to undertake all things for her. Whereupon ſhe communicated to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:33895:61"/>him her Deſign of diſpatching <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus,</hi> and propoſed to him the proper means for that end: He ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them, and they reſolved to caſt ſo horrid a Crime upon <hi>Gailan</hi> the Princes Confident, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex him in this Affair.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bozon</hi> went privately away from Court, taking ſuch perſons with him as he had an abſolute power over. He went to find out <hi>Gailan,</hi> to whom he ſaid he was reſolved to attempt <hi>Meroveus</hi>'s Liberty, whoſe misfortune he deplored, that he had ſeveral Friends in the Houſe he was in; that he hoped to oblige the Religious to leave him to him, and that he would then conduct him into <hi>Auſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> where the Queen his Wife would be ſure to receive him with joy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gailan</hi>'s Affection for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:33895:61"/>was too great to refuſe ſo fair a Propoſition. He encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <hi>Bozon</hi> to ſo fair and generous an enterprize, and aſſured him that if he was happy enough to bring it to paſs, the Prince would not be ungrateful. They went to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether to the place where he was, and <hi>Bozon</hi> made <hi>Gailan</hi> to expect him at the Door.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bozon,</hi> ſeeing the Prince, told him that the reſentment that he had of the ills that his Enemies made him ſuffer ſo unjuſtly, had brought him to that place, where, by the means of Prayers and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, he was ſuffered to come to him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> immediately interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him, to ask News of <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bozon</hi> aſſured him that ſhe reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:33895:62"/>peaceably in <hi>Auſtraſia,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing his diſcourſe, he related to the Prince that he was upon the point of returning thither; that if he would ſuffer himſelf to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted by his zeal, he would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure his liberty; that <hi>Gailan</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected them twenty Paces from thence with a Troop of truſty Men; that they would go together into that Country, where he did not doubt but the Queen would receive him with open Arms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> tranſported with joy, at this obliging Diſcourſe, embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced <hi>Bozon,</hi> told him that he would follow him where ever he would lead him, and ſwear to him that he would equal the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence to the greatneſs of the Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bozon</hi> told him that he needed only to come out, and that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:33895:62"/>who had care of the Door, attended. <hi>Meroveus</hi> marched im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately with him, they traver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the Cloiſters, and likewiſe paſſed the Door without any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacle; inſomuch that this Prince then fancied that Fortune, after ſo many outrages, would be at length reconciled to him. They went to <hi>Gailan</hi> and the other perſons with him. <hi>Gailan</hi> was in an extaſie to ſee his Prince again, for whom he had ſo tender and ſo ſincere an affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. This little Troop, without loſing any time, marched with all ſpeed towards <hi>Auſtraſia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When they were within a League of <hi>Metor, Bozon</hi> remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Prince, that it was not convenient to paſs further without giving the Queen notice, becauſe that the ſight of the Prince might allarm all the Court, who would imagine, with ſome appearance of
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:33895:63"/>reaſon, that it would be a new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of War with <hi>Chilperick;</hi> that therefore it was fit <hi>Gailan</hi> ſhould be ſent, who, being unknown, might the more eaſily, and without being ſuſpected, ſpeak in ſecret to <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> was loath to conſent to this Propoſition, becauſe his love drew him with too much vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence towards the Princeſs. But he was forced at length to yield to it, and durſt not openly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict <hi>Bozon. Gailan</hi> went from the Prince, in hopes of doing him an important Service; In the mean time he did not foreſee, that his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence would facilitate to the Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, the execution of their deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enterprize.</p>
               <p>After that <hi>Meroveus</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed himſelf ſometime, in a Country Houſe, <hi>Bozon</hi> asked him,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:33895:63"/>if he would not go meet <hi>Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Lover impatiently longing to ſee <hi>Brunchaut</hi> again, received this notice with joy. They all marched haſtily towards <hi>Metor,</hi> and when they were come into a Wood which was but half a League from it, <hi>Bozon</hi> having given the ſignal, to thoſe he had choſen for this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible Sacrifice, two of thoſe perfidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Wretches ſtabbed that unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Prince with their Ponyards, and bathed them in his Blood.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bozon</hi> returned immediately to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Paris,</hi> to give an account to <hi>Fredegonda,</hi> and the Aſſaſſinates according to the Order they had received, hid themſelves in the Wood, waiting for <hi>Gailan,</hi> who came ſome moments after. When he perceived <hi>Meroveus</hi> in ſo fatal a condition, he was ſeized with
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:33895:64"/>ſuch an horrour, which made him make a great ſhriek.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Meroveus</hi> at this noiſe opening his Eyes, and ſtill knowing <hi>Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> rallied all the Life he had left him, to ask him how the Queen did?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gailan</hi> ſaw that the Prince was upon the point of dying, and that all the help he endeavoured to give him would be uſeleſs; ſo that he thought of nothing, but ſatisfying his laſt deſire. He drew a Letter out of his Pocket, that <hi>Brunchaut</hi> had given him, and put into <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus</hi> his hands.</p>
               <p>The Prince re-aſſumed as much as he could his languiſhing looks, he fixed them upon this Paper, and it ſeemed as if Love ſtopped the ſtroke of Death, to permit this Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to enjoy this laſt delight. So
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:33895:64"/>that he had ſtrength enough to read the Letter; which is as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I Am extreamly grieved, Sir, to ſee that my Authority is not yet ſo well ſettled, as to go and receive you, with all the luſtre that my Devoir and my Love require. Be pleaſed to come this Evening ſecretly to Court with your Confident, who can intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce you to me, and We will adviſe together of the means to make you known to the People, without danger. Farewell. I impatiently long to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>BRUNCHAUT.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>As ſoon as the Prince had read theſe laſt words, he glewed his mouth upon the Paper, and breath'd his laſt in a great ſigh.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time the Murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:33895:65"/>thundered out of the place they were concealed in, upon <hi>Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> accuſed him of the Princes Death; and having ſeized him, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned towards <hi>Paris,</hi> and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the King. It was to no purpoſe this unhappy Man called Heaven to Witneſs his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and to make Oaths that cauſed aſtoniſhment and pity in all thoſe that heard him. <hi>Fredegonda</hi> upon the Depoſition of her Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, judged him Criminal, and even perſuaded <hi>Chilperick,</hi> who cauſed his Noſe and Ears, his Feet and Hands to be cut off.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Brunchaut</hi> had learn'd this Tragical Death, ſhe did not at all doubt from what hand the Blows came. She would have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded <hi>Chilperick</hi>'s Territories, but as the Publick Intereſt was more conſiderable than her own, her Council oppoſed this Deſign,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:33895:65"/>wherein there was more to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than hoped. Thus all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voir ſhe could practice towards <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roveus,</hi> was reduced to the giving him her Tears, and to nouriſh a long time deſires, without power, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge his Death.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:66"/>
            <head>Books Printed for <hi>R. Bentley</hi> and <hi>M. Magnes,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>THe Hiſtory of the Paſſions, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plato</hi>'s Apology for <hi>Socrates,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Idolatry, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi> of Hoſt-Worſhip, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Whitby</hi>'s Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Creſſey.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Chamberlain</hi>'s Poems, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Moral Eſſays, in 2 Vol. in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Proſpect of Humane Miſery, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Vanity of Honour, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Devotions, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Princeſs of <hi>Cleve,</hi> the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Romance, in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Memoirs of Madam <hi>Maria Manchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> in <hi>Octavo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Heroine Muſqueteer, in 4 parts, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Happy Slave, in 3 parts, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33895:66"/>
               <item>The Diſorders of Love, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Triumphs of Love, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Zelinda,</hi> A Romance, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Count <hi>Brion;</hi> or, the Cheating Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Obliging Miſtreſs, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fatal Prudence, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Count Cabalis, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Double Cuckold, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Almanzor</hi> and <hi>Almanzaida,</hi> in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Pilgrim, A Novel, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Princeſs of <hi>Monferrat,</hi> A Novel, in 2 parts.</item>
               <item>The Pilgrim, the 2d. Part.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Homais</hi> Queen of <hi>Tunis,</hi> A Novel.</item>
               <item>Gallant Memoires; or the Amours of a Perſon of Quality, in Twelves.</item>
               <item>Amours of the <hi>French</hi> King, and Madam <hi>Lavalieur.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amours of Madam—and the Count <hi>de</hi>—</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meroveus,</hi> A Novel.</item>
               <item>The Extravagant Poet, A Novel.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Plays Written by <hi>John Dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Eſq;</head>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Limberham,</hi> or the <hi>Kind-Keeper.
<pb facs="tcp:33895:67"/>Oedipus,</hi> in part.</item>
               <item>Miſtaken Husband, in part.</item>
               <item>Notes on <hi>Morocco,</hi> in part.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plays Written by Mr.</hi> Lee.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nero,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Glorian,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>The Rival Queens a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mythridates,</hi> a Tragedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plays Written by Mr.</hi> Crown.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Andromache,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Caliſto,</hi> A Maſque at Court.</item>
               <item>Country-Wit, A Comedy.</item>
               <item>Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in 2 parts.</item>
               <item>The Miſeries of Civil-War.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Plays Written by Mrs.</hi> Bhen.</item>
               <item>Forced Marriage, A Tragi-Comedy.</item>
               <item>Town-Fop, A Comedy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Abdellazar,</hi> A Tragedy.</item>
               <item>Madam <hi>Fickle,</hi> Comedies.</item>
               <item>Fond-Husband, Comedies.</item>
               <item>Virtuous Wife, Comedies.</item>
               <item>Plain-Dealer, A Comedy, By Mr. <hi>Wicherly.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>All Miſtaken, By Mr. <hi>Howard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monſieur, By Mr. <hi>Howard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Generous Enemies, A Comedy, By Mr. <hi>Corey.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33895:67"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tartuff,</hi> A Comedy; By Mr. <hi>Med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Orphan, Or the Unhappy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> Or the Force of Love.</item>
               <item>Souldiers Fortune.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth, with the Murther of the good Duke of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> in 2 parts.</item>
               <item>King <hi>Lear.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thyeſtes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tamerlane</hi> the Great.</item>
               <item>Moor of <hi>Venice.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Unhappy Favourite.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>French Books.</head>
               <item>La vie &amp; les faicts memorables de l'Eveſque de Munſter.</item>
               <item>Le Pelerin: Nouvelle Curieuſe.</item>
               <item>Hiſtoire du Grand Tamerlan.</item>
               <item>Les Satyres de Boileau.</item>
               <item>Tamerlan: ou la mort de Bajazet. Tragedie.</item>
               <item>Bellorophon: Tragedie.</item>
               <item>Inſtruction moralle d'une Pere a ſon fils.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Silvii,</hi> Opera Medica.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:33895:68"/>
               <item>Les Commentaires de <hi>Caeſar,</hi> par Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bancourt.</item>
               <item>La Noble Venitienne: Hiſtoire gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lante.</item>
               <item>Memoires de Pontis. 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>Memoires ſur l'origine des guerres. 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>Lacedemone antienne &amp; nouvelle. 2 Vol.</item>
               <item>Merovee fils de France; Nouvelle hiſtorique.</item>
               <item>Memoires de Madam de Ravezan, en 4 part.</item>
               <item>Madamoiſelle de Tournon.</item>
               <item>The third Volume of the Moral Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſays, in <hi>Twelves.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Tragedy in Heroick Verſe: Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by two Ladies.</item>
               <item>The Rival-Mother, a Novel.</item>
               <item>A perfect School for the Officers of the Mouth.</item>
               <item>The Emperour and Empire betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by whom and how,</item>
               <item>The Policy of the Clergie of <hi>France</hi> to deſtroy poor Proteſtants.</item>
               <item>Moral Eſſays, the fourth Volume, in the Preſs.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:33895:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
